<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gbv/dea_lod/main/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en" />
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en">Translation of a letter from Mr. Whitworth to Count
          Golofkin, about the affront offerd to Mr. Matveoff</title>
        <author xml:lang="en">Charles</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Whitworth</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Languages of Diplomacy Digital Edition</edition>
        <editor>
          <persName ref="#rjeoutski">
            <surname>Rjeoutski</surname>
            <forename>Vladislav</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#borisov">
            <surname>Borisov</surname>
            <forename>Viktor</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#kandakou">
            <surname>Kandakou</surname>
            <forename>Dzianis</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#lavrinovich">
            <surname>Lavrinovich</surname>
            <forename>Maya</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#sergeev">
            <surname>Sergeev</surname>
            <forename>Mikhail</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#herzog">
            <surname>Herzog</surname>
            <forename>André</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#wallner">
            <surname>Wallner</surname>
            <forename>Karin</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#pipka">
            <surname>Rißler-Pipka</surname>
            <forename>Nanette</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <orgName role="hostingInstitution" xml:lang="de">qed.perspektivia.net</orgName>
        </publisher>
        <authority>MWS-Netzwerk Osteuropa</authority>
        <pubPlace>Bonn</pubPlace>
        <date when="2024-08-30">30. August 2024</date>
        <availability xml:id="availability-textsource-1" corresp="#textsource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <availability xml:id="availability-imagesource-1" corresp="#imagesource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno>
          <idno type="project_id">lod</idno>
        </idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main" level="s">Languages of eighteenth-century diplomacy</title>
        <title type="sub" level="s">Russia in a European context</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>TODO</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="letter">
        <head>
          <title>21 September / 2 October 1708. – Translation of a letter from Mr.
            Whitworth{{p1255}} to Count Golofkin{{p0071}}, about the affront offerd to Mr.
            Matveoff{{p0699}}</title>
          <note>
            <bibl>NA Kew, Russia, no. SP 91-5, f. 96-99. English translation.</bibl>
          </note>
        </head>
        <pb n="f. 96" />
        <p>
          <placeName key="g0001" ref="https://www.geonames.org/524894">Mosco</placeName>
        </p>
        <p>21. Sept[embe]r / </p>
        <p>2 Oct[obe]r 1708</p>
        <p>Translation of a letter from Mr. Whitworth{{p1255}} to Count Golofkin{{p0071}}, about the
          affront offerd to Mr. Matveoff{{p0699}}</p>
        <p />
        <p>Last night I received the honour of your Excellencys Letter of the 16.th Inst[ant].
          concerning the Extraordinary affront offer’d to His Excellency your Ambassador Mons[iue]r
          Matveoff{{p0699}} in <placeName
            key="g0003"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName>, and the great concern of
          His Czaarish Majesty{{p0174}} : I am very confident and dare give you the most positive
          assurances, that H[is] C[zarish] M[ajesty]{{p0174}} himself cannot be more moved at this
          unluky accident, than the Queen{{p0668}} is, and that nothing shall be last undone which
          lyes in Her Majestys power, to let all the world see Her resentement on this occasion ;
          and to convince His Majesty{{p0174}} of the great Esteem She has, and allways will have
          for his person and friendship ; the annext copys of the two Letters from his Excellency
          the Secretary of State M[iste]r Boyle{{p1969}} to your Ambassador{{p0699}} which I
          received two days ago by a Courier from <placeName
            key="g0049"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/581049">Archangel</placeName>,
          express the sentiments of the Court{{o0002}} so fully on this occasion, tat it is not
          possible for me to find out Terms more strong or more oblidging ; you will theresee what
          that seventeen persons are allready in prison, and will be prosecuted with the outmost
          severity for this attempt : I own it is of such a nature that I shall not endeavour any
          wise </p>
        <pb n="f. 96v" />
        <p> to excuse their insolence ; but I must observe, that the Ambassadors Relation seems to
          be aggravated in so violent a manner, as is not usuall to persons of his prudence and
          moderation, who instead of endeavouring to lessen the friendship of their Principals,
          should soften the report of such inconveniences as may some times arrise throu the
          ignorance or ill manners of inconsiderable people : as Her Majestys Ministers could not
          expect to unkind a representation, after the many Civilitys he had received from them and
          all persons of quality and Distincion, they have not taken the precaution to give me a
          full information of the particulars ; however I shall write for one, and do not question
          but that will clear the Court{{o0002}} from several imputations ; In the mean time I shall
          onely observe, that his Excellency M[iste]r Secretary Boyle{{p1969}} in no less than three
          Letters positively mentions his having sent Secretary to take care of the
          Ambassador{{p0699}}, and get him released, as soon as ever he had notice of it, thou very
          late at night ; which is very far from the unworthy suspicion of M[iste]r
          Walpooles{{p1511}} coming of his own accord to divert himself at such a misfortune : I
          also find by several private Letters to me and other persons here, that the
          Ambassador{{p0699}} was not carryed to prison, but to the house of the Bailif, that not
          onely two but above ten Tradesmen, who are now in prison, ware concern’d in arresting him
          for debts, which ware much greater than he mentions, thou I cannot tell the particular sum
          ; nor do I find nor can believe, that ever any public notice </p>
        <pb n="f. 97" />
        <p> was given, or day appointed to pay his creditors ; for it is unreasonable to think any
          people should be so mad as to run themselves into these inconveniencys, when a time was
          named and they inform’d they should receive satisfaction ; which particulars I do not
          mention to excuse the fact, but onely to let you see, that some persons, who do not wish
          well to the peace of both crowns, have <hi rendition="#s">tacken</hi> taken pains to give
          His Exc[ellence] Mons[ieu]r Matveoff{{p0699}} as bad impression of this matter as ever
          they would.</p>
        <p>You will see by the inclosed copys that your Ambassador{{p0699}} was leaving great
          Britain, and His Exc[ellency] the Secretary Boyle{{p1969}} informs me, that he had
          declar’d [?] to receive a very valuable present from Her Majesty{{p0668}}, to make use of
          a Yacht for his Transportation, or even to take his recredentials, notwithstanding all
          possible diligence was using, according to the course of our Laws, for making reparation,
          and his presence would have been very agreable till the wholle was effected ; for my part
          I shall immediately give Her Majesty{{p0668}} an account of your desires &amp; by my
          representations heartily contribute all that lyes in my power, towards procuring a
          suitable satisfaction, and maintaining the old friendship between the two Dominions of
          Great Britain and Great Russia ; hoping at the same time your Exc[ellence] will endeavour,
          as you ware pleased to promiss, to moderate by your good officies His Czarish
          Maj[esty]{{p0174}} resentement and facilitate the way on your side ; if I thought my
          presence might be acceptable or of use to this good work; I hall willingly wait </p>
        <pb n="f. 97v" />
        <p> upon His Cz[arish] Maj[esty]{{p0174}} and your Exc[ellence]: with a great deal of
          pleasure, at any time and place you may think fit to appoint me, both to give by word of
          mouth the further assurances of Her Majestys great concern at this affair, and to
          deliberate on the most proper means for bringing it to a [?] conclusion ; and Her
          Majesty{{p0668}} has even under consideration if it be demanded to send person of quality
          express to His Cz[arish] Maj[esty]{{p0174}} as a further proof of Her Esteem.</p>
        <p>From all what I have here related I hope you will own such case is taking fir suitable
          and speedy reparation, that you have no reason to think of any other method, or to impute
          this unluky accident, which could not possibly be foreseen and therefor not prevented, to
          Her Majesty{{p0668}} or the Government, much less to let it have any impression on the
          present friendship and good Correspondence between the two Crowns ; which I hope is built
          upon more solid principles, than to be shaken by such occasions, considering the vast
          benefits that daily accrue and still may increase to this Empire from that of Great
          Britain ; and as to Her Majestys Friendship and strength, it is too much valued in most
          places of Europe to be slighted, especially in the present juncture, when you must be
          sensible, that many people would gladly lay hold for any occasion, to make a breach or
          even a coldness between the two Crowns ; but that, I am fully persuaded, as long as His
          Cz[arish] Maj[esty]{{p0174}} has such prudent Councillors as you are, will never happen
          and on the other side I shall allways do my best, to </p>
        <pb n="f. 98" />
        <p> find out opportunitys, whereby the Czar{{p0174}} may be induc’d to encrease the Esteem
          he has often profess’d to me to have for Her Majestys, and that gracious regard He has
          hitherto shown for Her Subjects, by whom he has several times own’d he is well serv’d.</p>
        <p>After having detain’d Your Excellency thus long I shall be very short in those points,
          which relate to me and the Consul{{p1252}} ; which thou it is true are not to be compared
          with the great affront unlukely happen’d to M[iste]r Artemonowitz{{p0699}}, yet have been
          of weight and might have been of more, if ill represented ; and as to the satisfaction
          obtain’d, I am oblig’d to say it has never been without a great deal of pains and
          disagreableness, and then not proportionable to the affronts : as for the people that
          attack’d me and my servants with stones, they knew very well who I was, for my Equipage
          was not so common as not to be easily distinguish’d, and my servants nam’d my character
          several times ; that the stones did not hit me was my good <hi rendition="#s">look</hi>
          luck and not their good manners, for they ware indifferently fluny [?], and two offer’d to
          lay hoe’d on my bridle, and had my horse given way to them, I cannot tell how they might
          have treated me then : as to their hard bodily punishment it was the commonest in this
          Country, and then taken barely pro formû, my secretary onely permitting them to have four
          of five blows, and that from the two alone, who would have seized my horse, thou above
          twenty ware concern’d in the uproar ; as to my goods being seal’d up, </p>
        <pb n="f. 98v" />
        <p> I had not acquainted your Precasse{{o0064}} with the place whither I sent them, because
          I left servants in Town to take care of them, they being onely laid in one of the Consuls
          warehouses to avoid fire and thieves, against which I had no other place of security ; nor
          could the Town Councill pretend ignorance whose they ware, since my servants appear’d
          there in my Livery, to acquaint them of it before they ware sealed up, and thou I
          represented this in <placeName
            key="g0264"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/627904">Grodno</placeName>, yet the seals were not
          taken off in some months, till after my arrival in <placeName
            key="g0001"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/524894">Mosco</placeName>}
          : it is true a Consul can be brought into no Comparison with Ambassadors and Envoys, that
          is as to the rangs and other prerogatives, but the Laws of Nations also takes care for the
          protection of their persons, their houses and servants, nor did the two Instances I
          mention’d about M[iste]:r Goodfellow{{p1252}} Her Majestys Consul and Agent General any
          wise relate to his Trafick or the pretensions of her precauses might have on him ; but
          ware particular affronts done to his house ; but I avoid enlarging upon them, because they
          cannot help the present business and only might make it worse.</p>
        <p>As to the Recognition of King Stanislaus{{p0522}}, I find His Cz[arish]
          Maj[esty]{{p0174}} takes most amiss, that it was done without giving him any previous
          notice, at a time his Ministers ware treating a nearer allyance. All that I can at present
          add to what I lately writ to your Excellency on this point, is, that t’is probable I may
          have had orders to make such a notification a considerable time ago, if all the secretary
          of </p>
        <pb n="f. 99" />
        <p> States Letters were come to my hands, but yours Exc[ellency]: very well knows that near
          three months Letters from the 1. Febr[uary] to the las April are still missing nor have I
          yet received any duplicats of them by the present irregularity of the posts, so that I am
          entirely ignorant of all that was transacting at Court{{o0002}} in that time.</p>
        <p>I congratulate your Exc[ellency]: once more on the happy success of your arms, and wish
          the continuance thereof may crown all your endeavours ; for I am certain, Her Majesty the
          Queen{{p0668}} will have a very great satisfaction in every thing which may contribute to
          the wellfare of so good a friend and ally as She esteems His Cz[arish] Maj[esty]{{p0174}}
          : it is with very particular pleasure that I give your Exc[ellency]: these many
          assurances, to which I beg leave to add those of my being with great respect and Esteem</p>
        <p>C[harles] W[hitworth]</p>
        <p />
        <noteGrp>
          <note>See also:</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0009</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0014</note>
        </noteGrp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
