<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gbv/dea_lod/main/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en" />
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en">Extract of a Relation from Mr. Matveoff His Czarish
          Majesty's Ambassador dated in London the 23d of July 1708</title>
        <author xml:lang="en">Andrei</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Artamonovich</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Matveev</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Languages of Diplomacy Digital Edition</edition>
        <editor>
          <persName ref="#rjeoutski">
            <surname>Rjeoutski</surname>
            <forename>Vladislav</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#borisov">
            <surname>Borisov</surname>
            <forename>Viktor</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#kandakou">
            <surname>Kandakou</surname>
            <forename>Dzianis</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#lavrinovich">
            <surname>Lavrinovich</surname>
            <forename>Maya</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#sergeev">
            <surname>Sergeev</surname>
            <forename>Mikhail</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#herzog">
            <surname>Herzog</surname>
            <forename>André</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#wallner">
            <surname>Wallner</surname>
            <forename>Karin</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#pipka">
            <surname>Rißler-Pipka</surname>
            <forename>Nanette</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <orgName role="hostingInstitution" xml:lang="de">qed.perspektivia.net</orgName>
        </publisher>
        <authority>MWS-Netzwerk Osteuropa</authority>
        <pubPlace>Bonn</pubPlace>
        <date when="2024-08-30">30. August 2024</date>
        <availability xml:id="availability-textsource-1" corresp="#textsource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <availability xml:id="availability-imagesource-1" corresp="#imagesource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno>
          <idno type="project_id">lod</idno>
        </idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main" level="s">Languages of eighteenth-century diplomacy</title>
        <title type="sub" level="s">Russia in a European context</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>TODO</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="letter">
        <head>
          <title>23 July 1708. – Extract of a Relation from Mr. Matveoff{{p0699}} His Czarish
            Majesty’s Ambassador dated in <placeName
              key="g0003"
              ref="https://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName> the 23d of July
            1708</title>
          <note>
            <bibl>NA Kew, Russia, no. SP 91-5, f. 136-137v. English translation.</bibl>
          </note>
        </head>
        <pb n="f. 136" />
        <p>Extract of a Relation from Mr. Matveoff{{p0699}} His Czarish Majesty’s Ambassador dated
          in <placeName
            key="g0003"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName> the 23d of July 1708</p>
        <p />
        <p>After I have received my Audience of Leave at <placeName
            key="g0230"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/2633842">Windsor</placeName>
          on the 18<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>. Inst[ant]: from Her Majesty the Queen{{p0668}} with
          all gracious Expressions of favours for my Person and great assurances of friendship to
          His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}}, I return’d to <placeName
            key="g0003"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName>, and
          made preparations for my voyage to Holland according to your orders ; but having been
          oblig’d to contract some debts in the time my Bills of Exchange did not come on by the Hop
          of the posts, as soon as ever they arrived, I begun to account with my Creditors, had
          satisfied the most, as appears by their acquittances, and publickly fix’d the Term of the
          22d. July for rekoning and paying the rest.</p>
        <p>The 21<hi rendition="#sup">st</hi>. Inst[ant]: I went out of my house between eight and
          nine in the Evening, to speak with the forreign Ministers, who usually meet together on
          Wednesday every week in Sommerset house, to communicate the news, they received by the
          posts, and converse one with an other ; but as I pass’d in my Coach throu the Street where
          the Duke of Boltons{{p1970}} house stands, I was violently and cruelly attack’d at that
          time of night by some persons, </p>
        <pb n="f. 136v" />
        <p> who without giving me notice of any order, or telling me any reason stop’d my Coach,
          beat away my footmen, and then two forc’d themselves in to me, while the third set himself
          by my Coachman on the box, and drove away a fast as he could : They that were in the Coach
          took from <hi rendition="#s">my</hi> me my Sword, cane and hat and had the Confidence to
          affront and beat me inhumanely, so that I expected to be lost in this murderous attack,
          and therefore call’d out for help and assistance as loud as I could ; these Highwaymen
          continuing in the mean time to beat me, to hold me fast by my coat and pockets, till they
          ware quite torn, and to treat me barbarously beyond Expression : On my calling out, the
          people in Charls Street came together, stop’d my Coach, took me out of these vilains
          hands, and brought me in this ill Condition into a neighbouring Tavern, where these
          Highwaymen acquainting them that I was seized by order of the Sheriff for a debt of fifty
          pound, which I ow’d two Tradesmen for Laces etc: The people retir’d themselves and left me
          to the Disertion of these Robbers, who carried me with force out of the Tavern flung me
          into a Hackney Coach and brought me into a prison, where persons are used to be laid for
          great debts ; and had not a French Surgeon call’d La Fache{{p1968}}, </p>
        <pb n="f. 137" />
        <p> whom I knew, been there to my good fortune, and set himself in the Coach with me these
          vilains the Baylyfs had either murderd me, or carryed me to some distant place, that their
          scandalous action might not be discover’d. As I had sent a person from the Tavern to the
          forreign Ministers, who, as mention’d ware assembled in Sommerset house to acquaint them
          with this unheard off affront, they immediately took it for a common cause, and the Envoy
          of Florence{{p2135}} with Mylord Lyffort came to me into the prison, whilst the Envoy of
          Portugal{{p1961}} with Mylord Feversham{{p1971}} went the same moment to the Secretary of
          State M[iste]r Boyle{{p1969}} to acquaint him with this violent proceeding ; but not
          finding him (thou they sought him up and down) they came back to me in the prison call’d
          black Reff ; whither his Secretary M[iste]r Walpoole{{p1511}} likewise came, and finding
          me arrested for such a small debt, and so affronted, contrary to the Law of Nations, he
          took a memorandum of it, promising that the Secretary of State{{p1969}} would come to me
          the next day, and make a very sharp inquiry into what had happen’d. Of all this cruell
          treatment the forreign Ministers themselves </p>
        <pb n="f. 137v" />
        <p> were witness to their great astonishment, and stayd with me in the prison till two in
          the morning ; in which time having learnt the reason of my arrest, and finding no
          assistance from any one, I order’d the debt pretended from me to be immediately payd by
          advice of the forreign Ministers to free myself from this shamefull prison, from where the
          said Ministers and Lords being my particular friends carryed me home : Next morning all
          the forreign Ministers came to condole with me for this affront, the like where is to be
          found in no History, promisisng to engage in it as in the common cause etc: On which I
          immediately sent a memorial to the Secretary of State M[iste]r Boyle{{p1969}},
          representing this violation of the Law of Nations, and the affront done to His Czarish
          Majesty{{p0174}} in my Person and Character, that it might be laid before Her
          Mejesty{{p0668}}, and a suitable redress obtain’d : The said Secretary of State{{p1969}}
          came himself to me in the Evening, expressing his great Concern at my misfortune and
          affront, and promising to obtain me due Satisfaction from Her Majesty{{p0668}} without
          delay, to whom I on the contrary declar’d that in case it did not follow immediately, and
          in such a manner as was proportionable to the greatness of the unparallel’d affront, I
          should be oblig’d to go away without receiving my recredentials : what will be the Issue
          of this business, I shall hereafter give you an account</p>
        <p />
        <noteGrp>
          <note>See also:</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0009</note>
          <note> en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0013</note>
        </noteGrp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
