<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gbv/dea_lod/main/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en" />
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en">Translation of Count Golloffkin's Letter to Mr. Whitworth,
          about the affront offerd [to] the Russian Ambassador in London, dated from the camp at
          Grigorkow 16. Sept[ember] 1708 </title>
        <author xml:lang="en">Gavriil</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Ivanovich</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Golovkin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Languages of Diplomacy Digital Edition</edition>
        <editor>
          <persName ref="#rjeoutski">
            <surname>Rjeoutski</surname>
            <forename>Vladislav</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#borisov">
            <surname>Borisov</surname>
            <forename>Viktor</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#kandakou">
            <surname>Kandakou</surname>
            <forename>Dzianis</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#lavrinovich">
            <surname>Lavrinovich</surname>
            <forename>Maya</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#sergeev">
            <surname>Sergeev</surname>
            <forename>Mikhail</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#herzog">
            <surname>Herzog</surname>
            <forename>André</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#wallner">
            <surname>Wallner</surname>
            <forename>Karin</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#pipka">
            <surname>Rißler-Pipka</surname>
            <forename>Nanette</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <orgName role="hostingInstitution" xml:lang="de">qed.perspektivia.net</orgName>
        </publisher>
        <authority>MWS-Netzwerk Osteuropa</authority>
        <pubPlace>Bonn</pubPlace>
        <date when="2024-08-30">30. August 2024</date>
        <availability xml:id="availability-textsource-1" corresp="#textsource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <availability xml:id="availability-imagesource-1" corresp="#imagesource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno>
          <idno type="project_id">lod</idno>
        </idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main" level="s">Languages of eighteenth-century diplomacy</title>
        <title type="sub" level="s">Russia in a European context</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>TODO</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="letter">
        <head>
          <title>5 / 16 September 1708. – Translation of Count Golloffkin's{{p0071}} Letter to Mr.
            Whitworth{{p1255}}, about the affront offerd [to] the Russian Ambassador in London,
            dated from the camp at <placeName
              key="g0427"
              ref="https://www.geonames.org/628062">Grigorkow</placeName> 16. Sept[ember] 1708</title>
          <note>
            <bibl>NA Kew, Russia, no. SP 91-5, f. 69-71v. English translation.</bibl>
          </note>
        </head>
        <pb n="f. 69" />
        <p> Duplicate</p>
        <p>Translation of Count Golloffkin's{{p0071}} Letter to Mr. Whitworth{{p1255}}, about the
          affront offerd [to] the Russian Ambassador in London, dated from the camp at <placeName
            key="g0427"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/628062">Grigorkow</placeName> 16. Sept[ember] 1708</p>
        <p />
        <p>I have received your letter of the 3./14. Inst[ant] some days ago, by which I first was
          surprised, but when the particular Relation of our Ambassador Mr. Matveoff{{p0699}}
          afterwards came on, was quite astonish’d, to learn the unheard off inhuman Proceedings and
          affront offer’d His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}} himself in the person of His Ambassador at
          London, to the greatest violation of the Law of Nations. The Circumstances of this injury
          as the Ambassador has given an account to His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}}, are so very
          Extraordinary, that it must said to be an Instance without Example; namely that an
          Ambassador of so great a Prince, under the pretence of orders from a justice of peace, was
          permitted to be violently attack’d, in the open street, at night, by a parcel of Bailiffs
          or to call them more properly Highwaymen, his footmen beat off, his coach forceably broke
          open, these fellows placed by him, his person inhumanely treated with cudgelling, taking
          away his Sword, cane, and Hat, and tearing his apparel; and when by repeated outerys he
          had induced several persons to come to his assistance, who rescued him out of the hands of
          these Highwaymen and brought him into a neighbouring Tavern, to inform themselves of the
          busines ; the said fellows produced their orders, on which the Ambassador found himself
          again abandon’d by every one, turn’d over to the </p>
        <pb n="f. 69v" />
        <p> Didcretion of these thieves, further abused by them, forceably slung into a Harkney
          coach, hurried away to a scandalous prison, and there set fast ; and notwithstanding He
          the Ambassador sent some foreign Ministers and English Lords, who were his personal
          friends and took his part, to acquaint the Secretary of State with these unheard off
          proceedings, yet he would not be found, but his secretary Walpole{{p1511}} came thither,
          as he gave out of his own accord, and not as you report, dispatch’d by the Secretary of
          State, much less to the Ambassadors assistance, but perhaps to divert himself with the
          spectacle ; since he did not make the least offer for his release, nor once examin any
          person, how they durst thus misuse an Ambassador against the Law of Nations, but went away
          without doing any thing ; so that the Ambassador finding himself exposed without any
          Protection from the Government, was obliged to buy himself out of this jayl and barbarous
          hands, would He recover his Liberty, thou no other reason could be given him for this
          inhumane treatment, than that it was done at the suit of two Tradesmen for fifty pound
          Sterling, which the Ambass[ador] owd them, notwithstanding he had some time before
          appointed the next day for the payment of all debts, recredentials, his passport, nor
          procured a Jacht, son so that he could not have gone away from them. His Czarish
          Majesty{{p0174}} cannot do otherwise, than look on this unexpected affront with the
          greatest resentment, and therefore has graciously order’d me to write to you that you may
          acquaint Her Majesty of Great Britain{{p0668}}, how </p>
        <pb n="f. 70" />
        <p> sensible His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}} is at this proceeding, and that he demands from
          Her Majesty{{p0668}} a great satisfaction proportionable to the affront; to wit, that the
          Criminals and first the Sheriff, the occasion of all this Mischief may ay least be
          condemned to death, afterwards diverted of all his Employments and declared infamous that
          his servants who attack’d the Ambassador as Highwaymen in the open street, and treated him
          so barbarously, may be actually put to death as the most notorious Robbers and violators
          of the Law of Nations ; and that the Tradesmen (: who probably made this attempt on the
          Ambassador at the Instigation of some evil persons who were disposed to create a breach
          between the two crowns :) as well as all others any ways concern’d in this matter, should
          be also punished according to the severity of the Laws, that Her Majesty{{p0668}} may
          hereby convince the world of Her love to justice, and Her sincere friendship for His
          Czarish Majesty{{p0174}}, as well as wash off the scandal of violating the Law of Nations
          from Her people, since such an exemple was never known in any Country and much less
          amongst the Politer fort. For this affair cannot be repaired or made good in any other
          manner, and in default of such a suitable satisfaction, His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}} shall
          be oblig’d to do himself full justice, thou he would not willingly go so far, because of
          the Esteem and friendship he has for Her Majesty{{p0668}} ; to prevent which ill
          Consequences, you as an experienc’d Minister and true servant of the Queen{{p0668}}, will
          use your best endeavours by your representations, both to Her Majesty{{p0668}} and Her
          Ministers, that the old friendship </p>
        <pb n="f. 70v" />
        <p> and good correspondence, which has all along subsisted between the two Monarchs, and
          Empires of Great Russia and Great Britain, may suffer no diminution ; and wee on our sides
          shall likewise employ our best offices not to let it come to such ill effect.</p>
        <p>As to the disagreable accident which you mention, happen’d to you in our Country, from
          some ignorant people, you will easily judge they cannot be brought into comparison with
          the unheard off affront offer’d to our Ambassador, nevertheless we by His Czarish
          Majesty{{p0174}} orders have not suffer’d them to pass without giving you satisfaction ;
          for the first, when certain people who did not know your servants, had the boldness to
          fling stones at them; thou they did not touch your person in the least, yet the underwent
          hard bodily punishment in the presence of one you deputed for that purpose, till he said
          it was sufficient. As to the sealing up of your furniture in the Consuls warehouse, in the
          market place, it cannot be construed as any affront to you, since before your journey you
          did not inform the Posolsky Precasse{{o0064}} that your goods would be deposed there as is
          usuall in like cases, and while the Town Councill had some pretensions on the
          Consul{{p1252}} and other accounts to settle with him about the toll etc. They sealed up
          the said warehouse not knowing your goods were there ; nevertheless His Czarish
          Majesty{{p0174}} so soon as you complained thereof, reprimended the said Town Councill in
          very severe Terms, and with Indignation let them understand that they should immediately
          take off the seal from that warehouse where your things were : but for what relates to the
          Consul{{p1225}} </p>
        <pb n="f. 71" />
        <p> his person cannot be brought into competition with an Envoy and much less an Ambassador,
          and since he moreover drives a great Trade, he has sometimes disputes with several persons
          and offices, nevertheless if any thing were put upon him indecently, and complained off by
          him either to the Czar{{p0174}} or the Posolsky Precasse{{o0064}}, His Czarish
          Majesty{{p0174}} would not have fail’d to order him sufficient reparation in consideration
          of the Queen{{p0668}}.</p>
        <p>Lastly for what relates to the Queens recognition of Lezinsky{{p0522}}, which you have
          communicated to us, by the Queens orders ; but that it was done on repeated solicitations,
          after a long delay and the example of other Princes, and that Her Majesty{{p0668}} had not
          the last intention to prejudice the Czars interest thereby, but rather assured him of Her
          unalterable friendship : His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}} receives this Declaration with
          thanks but at the same time refers it to Her Majestys own mature reflection, whether it
          must not be very sensible to him, that Her Majesty{{p0668}} would make this step without
          any weighty reason, and without giving him any previous notice, in the very instant that
          His Ministers in London and the Hague were treating of a nearer allyance and conjunction
          between the two Crowns, and notwithstanding the Republick of Poland had desir’d Her
          Majesty{{p0668}} to deferr it for some little time. It is very true that His Recognition
          cannot in the least prejudice the Interest of His Czarish Majesty{{p0174}} or the common
          wealth, only that it may awaken some small discontent in his friends, and some pleasure in
          His Ennemys ; but being now pass’d it must be left </p>
        <pb n="f. 71" />
        <p> as it is, and the Decision thereof referr’d to the Will of God and chance of arms, which
          alone can decide, who is to keep possession of the Polish throne, and have of late been
          very favourable to His Majesty ; the Most High God give his further blessin and happy
          conclusion hereof, to whose allmighty protection &amp; recommend you and remain.</p>
        <p />
        <noteGrp>
          <note>See also:</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0013 ; </note>
          <note> en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0014</note>
        </noteGrp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
