<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gbv/dea_lod/main/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en"/>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en">Translation of Count Golloffkin's Letter to Mr. Whitworth,
          about the affront offerd [to] the Russian Ambassador in London, dated from the camp at
          Grigorkow 16. Sept[ember] 1708 </title>
        <author xml:lang="en">Gavriil</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Ivanovich</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Golovkin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Languages of Diplomacy Digital Edition</edition>
        <editor>
          <persName ref="#rjeoutski">
            <surname>Rjeoutski</surname>
            <forename>Vladislav</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#borisov">
            <surname>Borisov</surname>
            <forename>Viktor</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#kandakou">
            <surname>Kandakou</surname>
            <forename>Dzianis</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#lavrinovich">
            <surname>Lavrinovich</surname>
            <forename>Maya</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#sergeev">
            <surname>Sergeev</surname>
            <forename>Mikhail</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#herzog">
            <surname>Herzog</surname>
            <forename>André</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#wallner">
            <surname>Wallner</surname>
            <forename>Karin</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#pipka">
            <surname>Rißler-Pipka</surname>
            <forename>Nanette</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <orgName role="hostingInstitution" xml:lang="de">qed.perspektivia.net</orgName>
        </publisher>
        <authority>MWS-Netzwerk Osteuropa</authority>
        <pubPlace>Bonn</pubPlace>
        <date when="2024-08-30">30. August 2024</date>
        <availability xml:id="availability-textsource-1" corresp="#textsource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <availability xml:id="availability-imagesource-1" corresp="#imagesource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno>
          <idno type="project_id">lod</idno>
        </idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main" level="s">Languages of eighteenth-century diplomacy</title>
        <title type="sub" level="s">Russia in a European context</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>TODO</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    
    <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"/></xenoData><profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="letter">
        <head>
          5 / 16 September 1708. – Translation of <persName key="p0071">[the head of the Ambassadorial Chancery,] Count [Gavrila Ivanovich] Golloffkin</persName>'s letter to <persName key="p1255">[the Envoy Extraordinary of Great Britain to Russia,] Mr. [Charles] Whitworth</persName>,  about the affront offerd [to] <persName key="p0699">the Russian Ambassador in London [Andrei Artamonovich Matveev]</persName>, dated from the camp at <placeName key="g0427" ref="https://www.geonames.org/628062">Grigorkow</placeName> 16.
            Sept[ember] 1708
          <note><bibl>TNA Kew, Russia, no. SP 91-5, f. 69-71v. English translation.</bibl>
          </note>
        </head>
        <pb n="f. 69"/>
        <p> Duplicate</p>
        <p>Translation of <persName key="p0071">Count Golloffkin</persName>'s Letter to <persName key="p1255">Mr. Whitworth</persName>, about the affront offerd [to] <persName key="p0699">the Russian Ambassador in London</persName>, dated from the camp at <placeName key="g0427" ref="https://www.geonames.org/628062">Grigorkow</placeName> 16. Sept[ember]
          1708</p>
        <p/>
        <p>I have received your letter of the 3./14. Inst[ant] some days ago, by which I first was
          surprised, but when the particular Relation of our <persName key="p0699">Ambassador Mr.
          Matveoff</persName> afterwards came on, was quite astonish’d, to learn the unheard off
          inhuman Proceedings and affront offer’d <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName>
          himself in the person of <persName key="p0699">His Ambassador at London</persName>, to the
          greatest violation of the Law of Nations. The Circumstances of this injury as <persName key="p0699">the Ambassador</persName> has given an account to <persName key="p0174">His
          Czarish Majesty</persName>, are so very Extraordinary, that it must be said to be an
          Instance without Example; namely that an Ambassador of so great a Prince, under the
          pretence of orders from a justice of peace, was permitted to be violently attack’d, in the
          open street, at night, by a parcel of Bailiffs or to call them more properly Highwaymen,
          his footmen beat off, his coach forceably broke open, these fellows placed by him, his
          person inhumanely treated with cudgelling, taking away his Sword, cane, and Hat, and
          tearing his apparel; and when by repeated outerys he had induced several persons to come
          to his assistance, who rescued him out of the hands of these Highwaymen and brought him
          into a neighbouring Tavern, to inform themselves of the busines ; the said fellows
          produced their orders, on which <persName key="p0699">the Ambassador</persName> found
          himself again abandon’d by every one, turn’d over to the </p>
        <pb n="f. 69v"/>
        <p> Discretion of these thieves, further abused by them, forceably slung into a Harkney
          coach, hurried away to a scandalous prison, and there set fast; and notwithstanding <persName key="p0699">He the Ambassador</persName> sent some foreign Ministers and English Lords,
          who were his personal friends and took his part, to acquaint <persName key="p1969">the
          Secretary of State</persName> with these unheard off proceedings, yet he would not be
          found, but his secretary <persName key="p1511">Walpole</persName> came thither, as he gave
          out of his own accord, and not as you report, dispatch’d by <persName key="p1969">the
          Secretary of State</persName>, much less to the Ambassadors assistance, but perhaps to
          divert himself with the spectacle ; since he did not make the least offer for his release,
          nor once examin any person, how they durst thus misuse an Ambassador against the Law of
          Nations, but went away without doing any thing; so that <persName key="p0699">the
          Ambassador</persName> finding himself exposed without any Protection from the Government,
          was obliged to buy himself out of this jayl and barbarous hands, would He recover his
          Liberty, thou no other reason could be given him for this inhumane treatment, than that it
          was done at the suit of two Tradesmen for fifty pound Sterling, which <persName key="p0699">the Ambass[ador]</persName> owd them, notwithstanding he had some time
          before appointed the next day for the payment of all debts, recredentials, his passport,
          nor procured a Jacht, so that he could not have gone away from them. <persName key="p0174">His
          Czarish Majesty</persName> cannot do otherwise, than look on this unexpected affront with
          the greatest resentment, and therefore has graciously order’d me to write to you that you
          may acquaint <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty of Great Britain</persName>, how </p>
        <pb n="f. 70"/>
        <p> sensible <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> is at this proceeding, and
          that he demands from <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName> a great satisfaction
          proportionable to the affront; to wit, that the Criminals and first the Sheriff, the
          occasion of all this Mischief may ay least be condemned to death, afterwards diverted of
          all his Employments and declared infamous that his servants who attack’d <persName key="p0699">the Ambassador</persName> as Highwaymen in the open street, and treated him
          so barbarously, may be actually put to death as the most notorious Robbers and violators
          of the Law of Nations; and that the Tradesmen (: who probably made this attempt on <persName key="p0699">the Ambassador</persName> at the Instigation of some evil persons who were
          disposed to create a breach between the two crowns :) as well as all others any ways
          concern’d in this matter, should be also punished according to the severity of the Laws,
          that <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName> may hereby convince the world of Her
          love to justice, and Her sincere friendship for <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName>,
          as well as wash off the scandal of violating the Law of Nations from Her people, since
          such an exemple was never known in any Country and much less amongst the Politer sort. For
          this affair cannot be repaired or made good in any other manner, and in default of such a
          suitable satisfaction, <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> shall be
          oblig’d to do himself full justice, thou he would not willingly go so far, because of the
          Esteem and friendship he has for <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName>; to prevent
          which ill Consequences, you as an experienc’d Minister and true servant of <persName key="p0668">the Queen</persName>, will use your best endeavours by your representations,
          both to <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName> and Her Ministers, that the old
          friendship </p>
        <pb n="f. 70v"/>
        <p> and good correspondence, which has all along subsisted between the two Monarchs, and
          Empires of Great Russia and Great Britain, may suffer no diminution ; and wee on our sides
          shall likewise employ our best offices not to let it come to such ill effect.</p>
        <p>As to the disagreable accident which you mention, happen’d to you in our Country, from
          some ignorant people, you will easily judge they cannot be brought into comparison with
          the unheard off affront offer’d to <persName key="p0699">our Ambassador</persName>,
          nevertheless we by <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> orders have not
          suffer’d them to pass without giving you satisfaction; for the first, when certain people
          who did not know your servants, had the boldness to fling stones at them; thou they did
          not touch your person in the least, yet the underwent hard bodily punishment in the
          presence of one you deputed for that purpose, till he said it was sufficient. As to the
          sealing up of your furniture in the Consuls warehouse, in the market place, it cannot be
          construed as any affront to you, since before your journey you did not inform <orgName key="o0064">the Posolsky Precasse</orgName> that your goods would be deposed there as is
          usuall in like cases, and while the Town Councill had some pretensions on <persName key="p1252">the Consul</persName> and other accounts to settle with him about the toll
          etc. They sealed up the said warehouse not knowing your goods were there; nevertheless <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> so soon as you complained thereof,
          reprimended the said Town Councill in very severe Terms, and with Indignation let them
          understand that they should immediately take off the seal from that warehouse where your
          things were : but for what relates to <persName key="p1252">the Consul</persName>
        </p>
        <pb n="f. 71"/>
        <p> his person cannot be brought into competition with an Envoy and much less an Ambassador,
          and since he moreover drives a great Trade, he has sometimes disputes with several persons
          and offices, nevertheless if any thing were put upon him indecently, and complained off by
          him either to <persName key="p0174">the Czar</persName> or <orgName key="o0064">the
          Posolsky Precasse</orgName>, <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> would
          not have fail’d to order him sufficient reparation in consideration of <persName key="p0668">the Queen</persName>.</p>
        <p>Lastly for what relates to the Queens recognition of <persName key="p0522">Lezinsky</persName>,
          which you have communicated to us, by the Queens orders ; but that it was done on repeated
          solicitations, after a long delay and the example of other Princes, and that <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName> had not the last intention to prejudice the Czars
          interest thereby, but rather assured him of Her unalterable friendship: <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> receives this Declaration with thanks but at
          the same time refers it to Her Majestys own mature reflection, whether it must not be very
          sensible to him, that <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName> would make this step
          without any weighty reason, and without giving him any previous notice, in the very
          instant that His Ministers in London and the Hague were treating of a nearer allyance and
          conjunction between the two Crowns, and notwithstanding the Republick of Poland had
          desir’d <persName key="p0668">Her Majesty</persName> to deferr it for some little time. It
          is very true that His Recognition cannot in the least prejudice the Interest of <persName key="p0174">His Czarish Majesty</persName> or the common wealth, only that it may awaken
          some small discontent in his friends, and some pleasure in His Ennemys; but being now
          pass’d it must be left </p>
        <pb n="f. 71"/>
        <p> as it is, and the Decision thereof referr’d to the Will of God and chance of arms, which
          alone can decide, who is to keep possession of the Polish throne, and have of late been
          very favourable to His Majesty ; the Most High God give his further blessin and happy
          conclusion hereof, to whose allmighty protection &amp; recommend you and remain.</p>
        <p/>
        <noteGrp>
          <note>See also:</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0013</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0014</note>
        </noteGrp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>