<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gbv/dea_lod/main/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en" />
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en">Extract of the English Envoy's reply to Count Gollowin's
          answer dated Mosco 14./25. May 1705 </title>
        <author xml:lang="en">Charles</author>
        <author xml:lang="en">Whitworth</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Languages of Diplomacy Digital Edition</edition>
        <editor>
          <persName ref="#rjeoutski">
            <surname>Rjeoutski</surname>
            <forename>Vladislav</forename>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#borisov">
            <surname>Borisov</surname>
            <forename>Viktor</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#kandakou">
            <surname>Kandakou</surname>
            <forename>Dzianis</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#lavrinovich">
            <surname>Lavrinovich</surname>
            <forename>Maya</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/edt">editor</resp>
          <persName ref="#sergeev">
            <surname>Sergeev</surname>
            <forename>Mikhail</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#herzog">
            <surname>Herzog</surname>
            <forename>André</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#wallner">
            <surname>Wallner</surname>
            <forename>Karin</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/eng">technical infrastructure</resp>
          <persName ref="#pipka">
            <surname>Rißler-Pipka</surname>
            <forename>Nanette</forename>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>
          <orgName role="hostingInstitution" xml:lang="de">qed.perspektivia.net</orgName>
        </publisher>
        <authority>MWS-Netzwerk Osteuropa</authority>
        <pubPlace>Bonn</pubPlace>
        <date when="2024-08-30">30. August 2024</date>
        <availability xml:id="availability-textsource-1" corresp="#textsource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <availability xml:id="availability-imagesource-1" corresp="#imagesource-1">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/lincenses/by-sa/4.0/">
            <p>CC BY-SA 4.0</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <idno>
          <idno type="project_id">lod</idno>
        </idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title type="main" level="s">Languages of eighteenth-century diplomacy</title>
        <title type="sub" level="s">Russia in a European context</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>TODO</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="letter">
        <head>
          <title>14 / 25 May 1705. – Extract of the English Envoy's{{p1255}} reply to Count
            Gollowin's{{p0277}} answer dated <placeName
              key="g0001"
              ref="https://www.geonames.org/524894">Mosco</placeName> 14./25. May
            1705</title>
          <note>
            <bibl>NA Kew, Russia, no. SP 91-5, f. 90v-92. English copy.</bibl>
          </note>
        </head>
        <pb n="f. 90v" />
        <p>Extract of the English Envoy's{{p1255}} reply to Count Gollowin's{{p0277}} answer dated <placeName
            key="g0001"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/524894">Mosco</placeName> 14./25. May 1705</p>
        <p />
        <p>To the 3d. As if the Liberty granted to export the produce of their Tobacco Customfree
          was a particular favour of the Czar{{p0174}}, and no obligation as it is said, the Envoy
          might see from the words of the original Treaty, is answer’d : The Envoy has consulted the
          Treaty, and does find that a Liberty was given them to <hi rendition="#u">export such
          returns as they shall think fit, without laying any higher duty thereon than is payd at
          present by forreign Merchants</hi>. Now it is very well known, that by a Custome
          immemorial no forreign merchant ever did pay any duty for the Exportation of Russian
          Commodities, which he bought with the produce of such goods as had payd duty at their
          importation ; the Company{{o0137}} therefor having paid a very high duty for their Tobacco
          when brought in viz: 4. Copiks p. pound by the natural meaning of that clause they ware
          Customfree, especially since it was provided by the Treaty <hi rendition="#u">that if any
          difficulty not foreseen may arise in and about the Execution of this present grant, or the
          Const ruction thereof etc : all matters and things shall be favourably , liberally and
          beneficially construed and decided in favour and on the part</hi>
        </p>
        <pb n="f. 91" />
        <p>
          <hi rendition="#u"> of the said M ar quis or his assigns</hi>. It is likewise very plain, that the
          Czars Ministers themselves did for two years together own this to be the true intent of
          the Treaty, since for that time the indisputed liberty was given to export their goods
          Customfree, nor was it ever mention’d to be a new and particular grace of the
          Czars{{p0174}} either in the orders themselves, or in any writing, or by word of mouth to
          Mr. Goodfellow{{p1252}} ; thou had it been one, it was certainly great enough to deserve
          being insinuated to the Company{{o0137}}, and received by them with all dutyfull
          acknowledgment : from all which premises the Envoy is oblig’d to insist, that this
          Exportation Customfree is not a favour, but a justice to the said Company{{o137}}, and
          therefore he humbly hopes, it may still be complied with.</p>
        <p>As to the Letter of Exchange, which Mr. Consul Goodfellow{{p1252}} gave for 20 m. Rubels,
          it is said, not to have been done by force but voluntarily, in Consideration, that
          severall parcells of goods ware taken as part of payment for the Tobacco dutys as high
          rates, and other advantages allowed him and the Company{{o0137}} ; that the said Bill lay
          a year and a half impay’d, and that it was put to the Tobacco account not at a low but a
          reasonable price ; to all which is answerd : That the Envoy never said the Bill was taken
          by </p>
        <pb n="f. 91v" />
        <p> force, but on promise of having ready money immediately pay’d for it, which was not
          kept. As to the having given free carridges for the Tobacco ; that has hapned very
          seldome, and in such places, as hoses could not well be hired ; however these and such
          favours received, Mr. Goodfellow{{p1252}} allways was, and is still ready to acknowledge
          with his most humble thanks and the respect due to so greate a Prince. As to the not
          payment of this Bill, the Envoy begs leave to take notice, that there seems to be a small
          mistake ; for this Bill for 20 m. R Dollars was dated in Decemb[e]r 1702. and was duely
          pay’d in course ; but Mr. Goodfellow{{p1252}} gave in an other Bill for 24 m. Dollars in
          May 1703. which for want of a due indorsement was not pay’d till a considerable time
          afterwards. If this Bill for 20 m. R Dollars was plac’d on the Tobacco account not a t a
          low but at a reasonable rate, the Envoy hopes no difficulty will be made of having that
          reasonable rate replac’d by Russian money as it ought, and the Dollars henceforth
          transferr’d to the account for potash as he at first desir’d.</p>
        <p>As to the flax trade it is alleg’d, that this does not concern the Company{{o0137}}, but
          was given as a particular favour to the consul, with a prospect of increasing the Trade in
          the Esat Sea, whereof he gave some promices : to this answerd : </p>
        <pb n="f. 92" />
        <p> that the Envoy never said, this Trade concern’d the Company{{o0137}}, but begs leave to
          take notice, that there may be probably some little mistake on the second point ; for this
          patent was granted in July 1702. when the Czar{{p0174}} had no footing in Ingermanland,
          and much less any Haven on the East Sea ; for <placeName
            key="g0428"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/493970">Noteburgh</placeName>
          was not taken till September 1702. Neuenshantz etc. in 1703. and <placeName
            key="g0115"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/3247449">
          Narva</placeName> not till 1704. In the patet it is likewise mention’d to carry out the
          said flax by way of <placeName
            key="g0049"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/581049">Archangel</placeName>, which was the a great
          piece of service, none having been ever sent thither before, and lastly the
          Consul{{p1252}} had much ado, to obtain that the Town of <placeName
            key="g0115"
            ref="https://www.geonames.org/3247449">Narva</placeName>
          should likewise be inserted in his grant, in hopes a peace might be made before that was
          expired : however since His Excellence declares, that the common dutys ware onely order’d
          to be taken from him, and not the new additional impositions, the Envoy has nothing to
          desire, but that His Excellencys orders to this purpose may be signifyed to the
          Precasse{{o0064}}, in the usuall manner.</p>
        <noteGrp>
          <note>See also:</note>
          <note>en_na_russia_sp_91-5_0011</note>
        </noteGrp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
